Chapter 74. The sperm whale's head.
contrasted view.
Here now are two great whales laying their heads together. Let us join them
and lay together our own. Of the grand order of folio leviathans, the sperm
whale and the right whale are by far the most noteworthy. They are the only
whales regularly hunted by man. To the Nantucketer, they present the two
extremes of all the known varieties of the whale, as the external difference
between them is mainly observable in their heads, and as a head of each is
this moment hanging from the Peekquad's side, and as we may freely go from one
to the other by merely stepping across the deck, where I should like to know,
will you obtain a better chance to study practical Slogy than here?
In the first place, you are struck by the general contrast between these
heads. Both are massive enough in all conscience, but there is a certain
mathematical symmetry in the sperm whales, which the right whales sadly
lacks. There is more character in the sperm whale's head. As you behold it,
you involuntarily yield the immense superiority to him in point of pervading
dignity. In the present instance too, this dignity is heightened by the pepper
and salt color of his head at the summit, giving token of advanced age and
large experience. In short, he is what the fishermen technically call a gayheaded whale.
Let us now note what is least dissimilar in these heads, namely the two most
important organs, the eye and the ear.
far back on the side of the head, and low down near the angle of either
whale's jaw, if you narrowly search, you will at last see a lashless eye, which
you would fancy to be a young colt's eye, so out of all proportion is it to
the magnitude of the head.
Now, from this peculiar sideway position of the whale's eyes, it is plain that he
can never see an object which is exactly ahead, no more than he can one exactly a
stern. In a word, the position of the whale's eyes corresponds to that of a
man's ears, and you may fancy for yourself how it would fare with you did
you sideways survey objects through your ears. You would find that you could only
command some 30° of vision in advance of the straight sideline of sight and about
30 more behind it. If your bitterest foe were walking straight towards you with
dagger uplifted in broad day, you would not be able to see him any more than if
he were stealing upon you from behind.
In a word, you would have two backs, so to speak, but at the same time also two
fronts, side fronts. For what is it that makes the front of a man what indeed but
his eyes?
Moreover, while in most other animals that I can now think of, the eyes are so
planted as imperceptibly to blend their visual power, so as to produce one
picture and not two, to the brain, the peculiar position of the whale's eyes,
effectually divided, as they are by many cubic feet of solid head, which towers
between them like a great mountain separating two lakes in valleys. This of
course must wholly separate the impressions which each independent organ
imparts. The whale therefore must see one distinct picture on this side and
another distinct picture on that side, while all between must be profound
darkness and nothingness to him. Man may in effect be said to look out on the
world from a sentry box with two joined sashes for his window. But for the
whale, these two sashes are separately inserted, making two distinct windows,
but sadly impairing the view. This peculiarity of the whale's eyes is a
thing always to be borne in mind in the fishery, and to be remembered by the
reader in some subsequent scenes.
A curious and most puzzling question might be started concerning this visual
matter as touching the Leviathan, but I must be content with a hint. So long as
a man's eyes are open in the light, the act of seeing is involuntary, that is,
he cannot help mechanically seeing whatever objects are before him.
Nevertheless, anyone's experience will teach him that though he can take in an
undiscriminating sweep of things at one glance, it is quite impossible for him
attentively and completely, to examine any two things, however large or however
small, at one in the same instant of time. Never mind if they lie side by
side and touch each other. But if you now come to separate these two objects
and surround each by a circle of profound darkness, then in order to see
one of them in such a manner as to bring
your mind to bear on it, the other will be utterly excluded from your
contemporary consciousness. How is it then with the whale? True, both his eyes
in themselves must simultaneously act.
But is his brain so much more comprehensive, combining, and subtle
than man's that he can at the same moment of time attentively examine two
distinct prospects, one on one side of him and the other in an exactly opposite
direction? If he can, then is it a marvelous thing in him, as if a man were
able to simultaneously go through the demonstrations of two distinct problems
in Uklid, nor strictly investigated, is there any inongruity in this comparison,
it may be but an idle whim, but it has always seemed to me that the
extraordinary vacasillations of movement displayed by some whales when beset by
three or four boats, the timidity and liability to queer frights so common to
such whales. I think that all this indirectly proceeds from the helpless
perplexity of volition in which their divided and diametrically opposite
powers of vision must involve them.
But the ear of the whale is full as curious as the eye. If you are an entire
stranger to their race, you might hunt over these two heads for hours and never
discover that organ. The ear has no external leaf whatever, and into the
hole itself you can hardly insert a quill, so wondrously minute is it. It is
lodged a little behind the eye. With respect to their ears, this important
difference is to be observed between the sperm whale and the right, while the ear
of the former has an external opening.
That of the latter is entirely and evenly covered over with a membrane, so
as to be quite imperceptible from without.
Is it not curious that so vast a being as the whale should see the world
through so small an eye and hear the thunder through an ear which is smaller
than a hairs? But if the eye were broad as the lens of Hersel's great telescope
and his ears capacious as the porches of cathedrals, would that make him any
longer of sight or sharper of hearing?
Not at all. Why then do you try to enlarge your mind? Subtalize it.
Let us now, with whatever levers and steam engines we have at hand, can't
over the sperm whale's head, that it may lie bottom up, then ascending by a
ladder to the summit, have a peep down the mouth. And were it not that the body
is now completely separated from it, with a lantern, we might descend into
the great Kentucky mammoth cave of the stomach, but let us hold on here by this
tooth and look about us where we are.
What a really beautiful and chastel looking mouth from floor to ceiling,
lined, or rather papered with a glistening white membrane, glossy as bridal satins.
But come out now and look at this portentious lower jaw which seems like
the long narrow lid of an immense snuff box with the hinge at one end instead of
one side. If you pry it up so as to get it overhead and expose its rows of
teeth, it seems a terrific portal. And such, alas, it proves to many a poor
white in the fishery upon whom these spikes fall with impaling force. But far
more terrible is it to behold when fathoms down in the sea you see some
sulky whale floating there suspended with his predigious jaw some 15 ft long
hanging straight down at right angles with his body for all the world like a
ship's jib boom this whale is not dead he is only dispirited out of sorts perhaps hypocchondric
and so supine that the hinges of his jaw have relaxed leaving him there in that
ungainainely sort of plight, a reproach to all his tribe, who must no doubt
imprecate lock jaws upon him.
In most cases, this lower jaw, being easily unhinged by a practiced artist,
is disengaged and hoisted on deck for the purpose of extracting the ivory
teeth, and furnishing a supply of that hard white whale bone with which the
fishermen fashion all sorts of curious articles, including canes, umbrella
stocks, and handles to riding whips.
With a long, weary hoist, the jaw is dragged on board as if it were an
anchor. And when the proper time comes, some few days after the other work,
Quiqu Dagu, and Tashego, all being accomplished dentists, are set to
drawing teeth. With a keen cutting spade, Quiquay lances the gums. Then the
jaw is lashed down to ring bolts, and a tackle being rigged from a loft. They
drag out these teeth, as Michigan oxmen drag stumps of old oaks out of wild
woodlands. There are generally 42 teeth in all. in old whales much worn down but
undeayed nor filled after our artificial fashion. The jaw is afterwards sawn into
slabs and piled away like joists for building houses.